翻译：灰灰是菇凉
翻译：圈圈
翻译：小酸奶
校对：小酸奶
后期：吉吉
这是我的世界
This is my world.
恶劣  嵯峨  寒冷
Harsh, jagged, freezing.
不得不说
And I gotta say,
这简直太棒了
it's awesome!
这里什么都有
It's got everything.
冰  岩石  冰  雪  冰  有好多冰
Ice, rocks, ice, snow, ice. It's got a lot of ice.
很多现代化设施
Plenty of modern amenities.
最棒的是  大家都很快乐
And the best part, everyone's happy.
那是因为我们的世界是建立在石头之上的
That's because our world is built on a foundation of stones.
不是那些  是这些
Not those. These.
我们有书写在石头上的律法
See, we have these laws that are written in stone.
真正的书写在石头上
Literally, written in stone!
由守石人解释并执行
Interpreted and enforced by the Stonekeeper.
这些石头是保护我们安全的
The stones are here to protect us and keep us safe.
它们基本能告诉我们需要知道的一切
They pretty much tell us everything that we need to know.
重要的事  比如世界是如何创造的
Important stuff, like how the world was created
我们都是从伟大的天之牦牛屁股上掉下来的
when we all fell from the butt of the great sky yak
以及我们的世界是一座岛
and how our world is an island
它漂浮在无尽云彩组成的海上
that floats on a sea of endless clouds,
倚靠在大山地猛犸象的背上
resting on the backs of the great mountain mammoths.
我们得喂猛犸象吃冰  这样它们才不会过热
And how we have to feed ice to the mammoths, so they don't overheat
否则它们会死的
'cause if they did, they would die,
那样我们就会都掉进无尽的虚无
and we would all fall into the great nothing.
这里什么都没有
There's nothing down here!
但我最喜欢的石头
But my favorite stone of all
上面写着必须敲响铜锣
is the one that says the gong must be rung
叫醒发光的大蜗牛
to wake the great glowing snail
让它爬过天空  给村子带来光明
so it can crawl across the sky and bring light to the village.
我超爱那个
I love that one.
那可能是最重要的工作了
It might be the most important job of all.
不吹不擂  那份工作刚好属于我爸爸
And, humble brag, that job belongs to my dad.
他向这份工作倾注了他的激情  奉献
He does it with passion, commitment
还有他强健的助手的帮助...
and the help of his able-bodied assistant...
起来了  米果  该敲锣了
Up and at them, Migo! Time to ring the gong.
就是我
...me.
好嘞
Yes!
可以说  我在学习操作绳子
I guess you could say I'm learning the ropes
轮子
and the wheel
还有曲轴
and the crank
如果我爸爸不敲锣  我们就都处在黑暗中了
because if my dad didn't ring the gong, we'd all be in the dark.
发射
Launch!
这个活儿不容易
It isn't easy.
它需要技巧  胆量和决心
It requires skill, rock-solid nerves,
还有肩膀上的一个结实的脑袋
and a good, strong head on your shoulders...
因为真的没有其它办法可以敲锣了
...because there's literally no other way to ring a gong.
搞定
Oh, yeah.
这让我爸爸的生活有了重大意义
It gives my dad a great sense of purpose.
我说了  这是个重要的工作
Like I said, it's an important job,
终有一天  这个工作会传给我
a job that'll one day be mine.
干得漂亮
Whoa-hem Good one, Dam!
我等不及看到
And I can't wait for the day
我叫醒村子那天的到来了
that it's me who gets to wake the village.
*看下面的每个人*
*Look at everybody there below*
*那是我热爱并熟悉的雪人*
*All the yetis that I love and know*
*他们在醒来看这美好的早上*
*And they're waking up to see this awesome morning*
*他们都面带微笑*
*They've all got a smile*
*这是我爱这的另一个原因*
*on their face. Another reason I love this place*
*这里永远充满生机和乐趣*
*'Cause it's always full of life and never boring*
*看看我们周围*
*Look all around us*
*满是岩石和冰雪*
*It's all rock and ice and snow*
*滴水成冰地寒冷*
*Frigid and freezing*
*我知道  这样真美妙*
*Yeah, it's pretty great, I know*
*这是崭新的一天*
*And hey, hey. It's another day*
*正如每一天*
*Like every other*
*我什么都不想改变*
*I don't wanna change a thing*
*一点都不想改变*
*Not one little thing*
*石头说什么我就做什么*
*I mean, because I do what the stones say*
*我做得还不错*
*And I'm doing okay*
*有什么比这更好  这就是最好*
*What could be better than this? It is what it is*
*这就是完美*
*It is perfection*
*看大家各司其职  而且心情愉快*
*Look at everybody do their part and they do it with a happy heart*
*这让大家的生活都有了更大的意义*
*And it gives them all a sense of greater purpose*
*这就是*
*Well, that's the way that*
*我想要的生活  我要让大家都以我为傲*
*I wanna be I wanna make them all proud of me*
*做一个稳重的雪人  服务人民*
*Just be a steady yeti at their service*
你们真的相信猛犸象在支撑着我们吗
Do you seriously believe mammoths are holding us up?
-嗯  -什么在支撑着猛犸象
- Mmm-hmm. - What's holding up the mammoths?
听我来说  下面全都是猛犸象
Uh, hello. It's just mammoths all the way down.
别听他们的  他们在质疑石律
Don't listen to them. They're questioning the stones.
我们可不能质疑石律  对吧
And we don't do that. Okay?
*如果有问题  让你迷惑不解*
*If there's a question causing you to go astray*
*埋在心里  等你忘记就好了*
*Just stuff it down inside until it goes away*
-知道吗  -米果呢
- Got it? - Where's Migo?
米果  你永远不会成为敲锣人...
Migo, you will never be the gong ringer...
慢着  什么
Wait, what?
如果你不练习的话
...if you don't practice.
他要给你属于你自己的头盔
He's giving you your own helmet.
我搞砸了惊喜  抱歉  爸爸
Oh, I blew the surprise! Sorry, Dad.
属于我的头盔  难道今天就是注定的那一天
My own helmet? You mean today's the day?
恭喜你  米果
Congratulations, Migo.
今天是大日子啊  儿子
Big day, son!
各位  我要练习敲锣了
Hey, everyone, I get to do a practice gong!
*大家一起唱*
*And now we all say*
*这是崭新的一天*
*Hey, hey It's another day*
*正如每一天*
*Like every other*
*我什么都不想改变*
*And I don't wanna change a thing*
*一点都不想改变*
*Not one little thing*
*因为我们喜欢这样的生活*
*I mean because we like living this way*
*我们过得还不错*
*And we're doing okay*
*有什么比这更好*
*What could be better than this?*
*这就是最好  这就是完美*
*It is what it is. It is perfection*
*加油  米果  加油*
*You go, Migo, you go Whoa!*
*You go, Migo You go, whoa!*
*加油  米果  加油*
*You go, Migo You go*
*我说  嘟嘟嘟嘟嘟*
*I said doo-doo-doo, doo-doo*
*这就是完美*
*It is perfection*
*加油  米果  加油*
*You go, Migo You go, whoa*
*You go, Migo You go*
*我说  嘟嘟嘟嘟嘟*
*I said doo-doo-doo, doo-doo*
*这就是完美*
*It is perfection*
敲锣练习
Practice gong!
-敲锣练习  -敲锣练习
- Practice gong! - Practice gong!
-准备好了吗  -早就好了
- You ready? - Beyond ready!
真是迫不及待真正尝试一番了
Can't wait till this is my actual job!
对  马上你就要继承伟大的家族传统了
Yup. Soon you will join a long line of family greats.
平头叔叔  凹头爷爷
Uncle Flathead, Grandpa Smashhead,
架子头太爷爷  猛头婶婶  浆糊脑子舅舅
Great Grandpa Shelf head, Aunt Crushedhead, Uncle Mushbrain,
梆梆阿姨  没脖子南多  蹲蹲表哥
Aunt Bam Bam, No-neck Nando, Cousin Squatly,
道格和他的蠢木槌理论
Doug and his dumb mallet theory.
还是不提他了
We don't talk about him.
还有你妈妈
And your mom.
她要是在这里教你就好了
Wish she was here to teach you.
-你就教得很好  爸爸  -谢谢  儿子
- You're doing great, Dad. - Thanks, son.
好了  首先  检查风向
Okay, first, check your wind.
一点风就能把你吹得偏离正轨
Doesn't take much to blow you off course.
风向  没问题
Wind, check.
很好  下面是瞄准目标
Good. Now, true your aim.
如果不瞄准  那肯定不会成功
You'll never succeed if your aim isn't true.
目标  没问题
Aim, check!
好极了  下面的很重要
Great! Now, this is important.
-即使你知道会很疼...  -嗯
- Even though you know it's gonna hurt... - Mmm-hmm.
你也得用脑袋径直撞上去
...you gotta hit it head-on.
-真的很疼吗  -只有头两年吧
- Does it really hurt? - Only for the first year or two.
好吧  你以前是不是跟我一样高
Hmm. Did you actually used to be my height?
不是  我比你高多了
Nope, I was much taller.
我花了好多年才练成这样
Took me years to achieve this.
一天都没错过
Never missed a day!
-没错  -好
- Oh, yeah! - Cool!
-准备好了吗  -好了
- Ready? - Ready.
说出那个词吧  儿子
Say the word, son.
发射
Launch!
我告诉过你得抬起脚来吗
Uh, did I mention you gotta keep your feet up?
-没有  -你得把脚抬起来
- No. - You gotta keep your feet up.
知道了
Check.
好了  发射
Okay. Launch!
发射
Launch!
真没想到会这样
Never seen that happen.
发射
Launch!
好样的  米果
Attaboy, Migo!
咪琪
Meechee.
米果  瞄准目标
Migo, true your aim!
瞄准目标
True your aim!
-糟糕  -糟了
- Oh, no. - Uh-oh!
我的头盔  我的...
My helmet! Where's my...
那是什么
What is that?
不好  什么情况
Hey, hey! What?
快走开  走开
Go! Get away!
停  一点都不好玩
Stop it! Not funny! Aah!
看看你的小脚丫  小脚
Look at your small foot! Small foot.
小脚怪  小脚怪  天啊  是个小脚怪
Smallfoot. Smallfoot! Oh, my gosh, it's a smallfoot!
不  不  回来
Oh, no! No. Come back!
苍天啊
Oh, holy wowness!
各位  快来看
Everyone! You gotta see this!
过来  过来  过来
Come here! Come here! Come here!
各位
Hey, everyone!
-听我说  各位  -米果
- Listen, listen! Everyone! - Hey, Migo.
-你没敲到锣  -我知道
- You missed the gong. - I know.
-你没敲到锣  米果  -我知道
- You missed the gong, Migo. - I know.
快来  围过来  围过来  好
Come here. Gather round, gather round. Okay.
我看到一一个小脚怪
I saw a smallfoot!
-什么  -什么
- What? - What?
-什么  -好疼
- What? - Ow!
不信你们自己来看  快来
Just come here and see for yourself! Let's go! Come on!
我们走
Everyone, let's go!
他疯了
He's crazy!
爸爸
Dad!
那东西从天空中掉下来
It came at me from the sky.
是个闪闪发光的会飞的硬东西
It was like some sort of hard, shiny flying thing!
它发出的声音像...
It made a sound like...
就是此时它到了我跟前
And that's when it scooped me up!
看  就在这里
Look. It's right this way.
不  但是...
NO! But...
不不不
No! No, no! No!
本来就在这里的
It was right here!
我发誓  那个闪闪发光会飞的东西
I swear! This shiny, flying thing.
那个小脚怪就是从那里面射出来的
That's what the smallfoot shot out of.
咻的一下
It was like, poof!
然后有个像皮肤的大东西在它上面  就好像...
And then this big skin thing landed on top of it. It was like...
然后它看到了我  唱出了最奇怪最美妙的歌
And then it saw me, and it sang the most strange, beautiful song.
就这样...
It was like...
更像是这样...
Almost, it was more like...
说不定它还在附近
Oh, it's probably still around here somewhere.
我们找找吧  大家一起来
Let's look for it. Come on, everyone!
还在附近
Still around here?
-有可能在村子里  -有可能在我家里
- It could be in the village! - It could be at my house!
保护孩子们
Get the children!
米果疯了
Migo's gone crazy!
-他说看到了一个小脚怪  -可能吗
- He said he saw a smallfoot! - Is that possible?
你在这里
Oh, there you are!
-是真的吗  -等等  大家别慌
- Is it real? - Wait! Hold on! Everyone!
那东西看起来没那么可怕  其实还有点可爱
It didn't seem all that scary! It was kind of cute!
大家给我爸爸让路
Everyone, make way for my dad!
我是说守石人  抱歉  爸爸
Uh, I mean, the Stonekeeper. Sorry, Dad.
是守石人  快点  索普  你搞砸了
I mean, Stonekeeper. Come on, Thorp. You blew it.
大家早上好  你好吗
Good morning, everyone! Hey, how are you?
-天啊  -是因为米果没敲到锣吗
- Oh, boy. - Is this about Migo missing the gong?
守石人  他看到了一个小脚怪
Stonekeeper, he saw a smallfoot!
他说有可能还在附近
He said it might still be out there!
他说那是从天上掉下来的
He said it fell from the sky!
盖瑞  冷静  你知道自己不冷静会是什么样
Garry, calm down. You know how you get.
好吧  我尽量  不过我好怕
Okay, I'll try, but I'm just so scared.
我知道米果的小"故事"
Now, I know Migo has gotten
让大家都很紧张
you all very anxious with his little "Story,"
但大家不用害怕  因为那不是真的
but there's nothing to fear because it isn't true.
但我亲眼看到了
But I saw one!
不  你没有
No, you didn't.
我看到了
I did.
你不可能看到  因为根本不存在
You can't have seen it because it doesn't exist.
我知道  因为石律说没有小脚怪这种东西
I know. I know. Because the stone says there's no such thing as a smallfoot.
没错  说得一清二楚
Yeah, right there, clear as day.
我知道  但它就出现在了我面前
I know, but it was right there in front of me!
米果
Hey, Migo!
你怎么知道那是个小脚怪
How do you know it was a smallfoot?
因为它有个小脚
Because it had a small foot.
爸爸
Uh, Dad?
爸爸  显然他看到了什么东西
Daddy, clearly, he saw something.
我没有否认他看到了东西
Oh, I'm not denying he saw something.
极有可能他滑倒了
Most likely, he slipped,
撞到了头  撞傻了  看到了一头牦牛
hit his head, got confused, and saw a yak.
这下我明白了
Okay, I get it now.
如果米果说他看到了一个小脚怪
Because if Migo is saying he saw a smallfoot,
那他就是说石律是错的
then he's saying a stone is wrong.
你是这个意思吗  米果  石律是错的
Is that what you're saying, Migo? That a stone is wrong?
不  他不是那个意思
Nope! He is not saying that!
我来跟他谈谈  孩子嘛
Let me talk to him. Kids, right?
米果  你在干什么
Migo, what are you doing?
在全村人面前和守石人作对
Challenging the Stonekeeper in front of the whole village?
爸爸  你一直跟我说的那条建议是什么来着
Dad, what's the piece of advice you're always giving me?
"照别人说的做"
"Do what you're told."
-另一条  -"融入大家"
- The other one. - "Blend in."
另一条
The other one.
"听石律的话"  "做大家的一份子"
"Follow the stones." "Be a cog."
"做好自己的事"  "绝不对守石人提出异议"
"Do your part." "Never disagree with the Stonekeeper."
"永远坚持真理"
"Always be true!"
我那说的是敲锣  不是挑战石律
That was about hitting a gong. Not challenging a stone.
因为如果有悖于石律  那肯定是错的
'Cause if it goes against a stone, it can't be true!
可是如果我说我没看到小脚怪
But if I say I didn't see a smallfoot,
那我就是在说谎
then I'm lying.
米果
Migo,
你不是想当下一个敲锣人吗
I thought you wanted to be the next gong ringer.
是的
I do.
那你还说石律是错的吗
Then are you still saying a stone is wrong?
如果说我看到了一个小脚怪
If saying I saw a smallfoot
意味着石律是错的  那确实是这样
means that a stone is wrong, then I guess I am.
米果啊
Oh, Migo.
虽然这么说让我很心痛  真的
It pains me to say this. It truly does.
但你让我别无选择
But you leave me no choice.
违背石律是大不敬
Disobeying the stones is a grave offense.
从今天起  你将被驱逐出村子
From this day forward, you will be banished from the village!
-什么  -直到你准备好
- What? - Until you are ready
站在我们所有人面前
to stand before us all
告诉我们真相
and tell us the truth.
我说的就是真的
I am telling the truth.
就这样  各位  回去工作
That's all, everyone. Back to work.
继续过好完美的一天
Let's make it another perfect day.
守石人  拜托
Stonekeeper, please.
那是我儿子
That's my son.
给他点时间让他单独思考一下
Just give him a little time alone out there to think.
他会恢复理智的
He'll come to his senses.
-斯努兹  -喂
- Sooze. - Hey!
你被驱逐了  记得吗
You're banished, remember?
-你知道那是什么意思  -是的 索普
- You know what that means. - Yes, Thorp.
是吗  是什么意思
You do? What does it mean?
-索普  -来了
- Thorp! - Coming!
我们回头再聊
We'll circle back.
几乎没什么能在喜马拉雅山严酷寒冷的环境下生存
Few can survive the cold, brutal environment of the Himalayas,
但这种独特的生物可以
but this ingenious creature defies the odds.
那就是稀有的喜马拉雅跳蛛
The rare Himalayan jumping spider!
尽在本周《珀西・帕特森的野生动物》
This week on Percy Patterson's Wildlife!
这种敏捷的蜘蛛一次可产一千个卵
This agile arachnid can lay 1,000 eggs at a time
而且可以跳50英尺高
and can jump 50 feet into the air!
它肯定要好好准备一番
There's an element of mental preparation, I'm sure.
它在袭击我  糟了
It's attacking! Oh, no!
它的毒液要进入我的大脑了
The venom! It's going to my brain!
我的脸麻了
I can't feel my face.
继续拍  继续拍
Keep rolling. Keep rolling.
卡
Cut!
我要在你眼前融化了
I'm melting before your eyes.
-珀西  -我们加点特效上去
- Percy! - And we'll add an effect.
融化  融化  融化
Melting, melting, melting.
-珀西  -这段剪掉
- Percy! - Cut this bit out.
我要闭上一只眼
I'm gonna shut one of my eyes.
我的眼睛啊  好疼
Hey, my eye! My eye!
卡  你在干什么
Cut! What are you doing?
我在拯救我们的节目
I'm saving our show.
我被袭击会有很多人看的
Me being attacked would get huge ratings!
我们的节目是教育启发性节目
Our show is educational and enlightening!
要激起大家
A show that promotes respect
对地球上其它生物的尊重
for our fellow creatures on this planet.
我知道  所以才没人看
I know. That's why no one's watching.
所以我才不看
That's why I don't watch.
布兰达  除我们的蜘蛛跳部分外的桥段都很无聊
Look, Brenda, unless our spiderjumps, it's boring.
它跳起来了
Hey, it jumped!
真令人激动  拍下来了吗
Now, that was exciting. Did we film that?
当然没有了  好吧  那我过来
No, of course not. All right, I'll just have to go over here
采访一块树皮好了
and interview a piece of bark, shall I?
-雪怪  -什么
- Yeti. - What?
飞机坠毁在雪里
Plane crashed in the snow.
尖牙  利爪  庞然大物
Teeth, claws, huge!
我看到了一只雪怪
I saw a yeti!
你说雪怪
Yeti, you say?
我请你喝一杯  你给我详细说说
Let me buy you a drink, and you can tell me all about it.
-你相信我  对吧  -当然了
- You believe me, right? - Of course, I believe you!
真的吗  你可以相信我 我是飞行员
You do? You can trust me. I fly planes!
米果
Migo.
-是谁  -米果
- Who's there? - Migo.
是谁
Hello?
小脚怪  是你吗
Smallfoot? Is that you?
我可能是疯了  难怪没人相信我
Maybe you are going crazy. No wonder no one believes you.
我们相信你
We believe you.
你好
Hi.
米果
Migo.
-福林  -什么
- Fleem! - What?
伙计们
Heh. You guys.
只有我觉得他发现是我们后很失望吗
Is it just me, or does he look disappointed that it's us?
你想要所见之物的证据吗
You want proof that you saw what you saw?
-对  -我们有证据
- Yeah. - We got proof.
那你们相信我看到一个...
So, you believe me that I saw a...
一个小...
A small...
-他们在听  -谁
- They're listening. - Who?
压迫的隔墙之耳
The ears of oppression.
-对  -这...
- Yeah. - Uh...
这边来  隐匿模式
This way, stealth mode.
今天还能再怪一点吗
Could this day get any more bizarre?
太近了吗
Is this too close?
你知道你现在是什么吗
You know what you are now?
我们的人
One of us.
等等
Uh. Hey, wait up!
我们的人  我们的人  我们的人
One of us! One of us! One of us!
别告诉关吉是我说的  不过他有点多疑
Now, don't tell Gwangi I said this, but he's a bit paranoid.
福林  你是在说我吗
Fleem, are you talking about me?
明白我的意思吗
Do you see what I mean?
蔻卡跟石头说话  好像它们听得见一样
Kolka talks to rocks like they can hear her.
福林  嘘
Fleem! Shh!
他们说我讨厌  烦人  不消停
I've been told I'm pesky, annoying, and a real pain,
但有谁听妈妈的话啊  对吧
but, hey, who listens to their mom, right?
你们要带我去哪里
Where are you taking me?
我们的社长要求会面
Our leader requests a meeting.
慢着  你们有社长  是谁
Wait. You have a leader? Who?
到时候你就知道了
You'll see.
天啊
Oh, boy.
他来了
He's here.
-咪琪  -欢迎
- Meechee? - Welcome!
很高兴你来了
I'm really glad you're here.
什么
What?
这是什么地方
What is this place, exactly?
SES的秘密总部
The secret headquarters of the S.E.S.
"爱谁爱死"
The Esias?
不是不是  是三个字母  SES
No, no, no. It's three letters. Like S-E-S.
"小脚怪存在  傻逼"的英文缩写
Stands for "Smallfoot Exists, Suckas!"
福林  是"小脚怪论证社团"的英文缩写
Fleem, it's "Smallfoot Evidentiary Society."
我取的名字更好玩  但是...
I mean, my name's got a lot more pizzazz, but...
慢着  这是个小脚怪社
Wait. You're, like, a smallfoot club?
等等  你是社长
And hold on. You're the leader?
但你是守石人的女儿
But you're the Stonekeeper's daughter.
我爱我父亲
Look, I love my father,
但他并不是大家所说的"态度开明"
but he isn't exactly what you would call "Open to new ideas."
因为问题带来知识
Because questions lead to knowledge.
而知识就是力量
And knowledge is power.
所以说你们不止相信有小脚怪
So you don't just believe in the smallfoot.
你们还在寻找
You've been looking for one.
对  你看到那些"X"了吗
Yes. You see all the X's?
多年来我们找遍了整座山  就是想找一个
We have searched the entire mountain for years trying to find one.
你们为什么找"X"
Why are you looking for X's?
我们不是找"X"  而是找小脚怪
We're not looking for X's. We're looking for the smallfoot.
而你看到过一个
And you have seen one.
但我无法证实
But I can't prove it.
这就用到我们了
That is where we come in.
关吉  给他看证据
Gwangi, show him the evidence.
这就是你的证据
Here's your proof.
首先是小脚怪的皮毛
First item, smallfoot pelt.
这一证据证明它每年都会掉毛
Evidence suggests it sheds its skin annually.
其次是小脚怪角  我们觉得它只有一个角
Second item, smallfoot horn. We believe it only has one.
然后是这个
And then there's this.
无形智慧卷轴
The scroll of invisible wisdom.
想象一下他们放在这里的好东西
Just imagine the amazing stuff they put on here.
我觉得这都是胡扯
A bunch of crap, if you ask me.
这什么都证明不了
This proves nothing!
给他看最后一样
Show him the last one.
这是我发现的第一件证据
It's the first piece I ever found.
也是这一切的开始
It's the thing that started all of this.
那是触发器  他想起来了
That was a trigger. He's triggered!
你有小脚
Look at your small foot.
-你确实看到了  -它去哪里了
- You did see one. - Where did it go?
-我不知道  -努力想
- I don't know! - Think!
-到记忆深处  -扇他
- Reach into your memory! - Slap him!
不  它乘风飞过了云端
No! It got whisked away on the wind, over the clouds!
往哪飞了  往上  往一边  哪里
Which way? Up? Sideways? Where?
往下
Down!
你是说往下吗
Did you say down?
-扇他  -福林
- Slap him! - Fleem!
往下  当然了
Down! Of course!
我一直觉得
You know, I have always thought
山浮着是很奇怪的事
it was weird that a mountain floats
因为显然有无形的力量在把我们往下拉
when there's obviously some invisible force pulling us downward
让我们身边的一切不飘到空中去
and keeping everything around us from drifting off into the sky.
当然了  这只是理论
Of course, this is just a theory.
但这就是我们在这上面找不到的小脚怪原因
But that's why we haven't found one up here.
因为它是在下面这里
Because it's down here,
在云下面
below the clouds.
如果你要证据  我们就需要去那里
And if you want proof, that's where we need to go.
到虚无中去
In the nothing?
你们疯了
You're crazy.
不许说我疯
Don't call me crazy.
对  不许说一个疯子疯
Yeah. Never call a crazy guy crazy.
你们想知道为什么那叫"虚无"吗
You want to know why it's called the nothing?
因为那里什么都没有
Because there's nothing down there!
你为什么这么认为
Why do you believe that?
因为石律是这么写的
Because it's in the stones.
石律还说没有小脚怪呢
So is the one that says there's no smallfoot.
可你却看到了一个
And yet you saw one.
对  石律为什么要提到不存在的东西
Yeah. Why is there a stone that says something doesn't exist?
那不正证明它其实是存在的吗
Doesn't that just prove that it actually does?
如果一条石律是错的  那其它的也可能是错的
And if one stone is wrong, then others could be as well.
什么  其它石律  你觉得有多少是错的
What? Other stones? How many do you think are wrong?
整条绳子上的
The whole robe.
这一切都太疯狂了  我不参与了
You know what? This whole thing's insane. I'm out.
米果  等等
Migo, wait.
我只想证明我看到了一个小脚怪
Hey, I just wanna prove that I saw a smallfoot
好让我不再被驱逐
so I can get un-banished.
但是你呢  你想
But you, you wanna, what,
推翻我们这个世界的基石吗
tear down everything our world is built on?
重点不是推翻旧思想
It's not just about tearing down old ideas.
而是找到新的
It's about finding new ones.
你跟我来
You know what? Come with me.
*看看周围我们以为的这个世界*
*Take a look around and see the world we think we know*
*仔细看看*
*And then look closer*
*除了眼睛看到的美丽外表  还有更多*
*There's more to life than meets the eye a beauty to behold*
*世界比我们知道的大*
*It's all much bigger than we know*
*它只是刚开始在我们面前展开*
*It's only just beginning to unfold*
*让它都展开吧*
*So let it all unfold*
*远远超出你的思想所及*
*Far beyond all reason in your mind*
*有个神秘的世界等待你去探寻*
*There's a world mysterious there for you to find*
*我们一直都有的问题*
*All these questions that we always had*
*我们都很好奇  这没有什么不对*
*All we are is curious. There's nothing wrong with that*
*去探寻每一个角落*
*So go 'round every corner*
*探索每一天天空*
*Search every part of the sky*
*充满惊奇的生活*
*'Cause a life that's full of wonder*
*才是美妙的生活*
*Is a wonderful life*
*表面之下有我们要学习的东西*
*Dig beneath the surface find the lessons there to learn*
*然后深入研究*
*And then dig deeper*
*正视你的直觉  不要留一点遗憾*
*Feed your intuition. Don't leave any stone unturned*
*寻求真理*
*Be the seeker of the truth*
*响应它的召唤*
*Listen when you hear it calling you*
*你知道它在召唤你*
*You know it's calling you*
*远远超出你的思想所及*
*Far beyond all reason in your mind*
*有个神秘的世界等待你去探寻*
*There's a world mysterious there for you to find*
*我们一直都有的问题*
*All these questions that we always have*
*我们都很好奇  这没有什么不对*
*All we are is curious. There's nothing wrong with that*
*去探寻每一个角落*
*So go 'round every corner*
*探索每一天天空*
*Search every part of the sky*
*充满惊奇的生活*
*'Cause a life that's full of wonder*
*才是美妙的生活*
*Is a wonderful life*
米果  下面有个世界等着我们
Down there, Migo, a world awaits.
好  我去
Okay, I'll go.
-真的吗  -你有计划吗
- Really? - Do you have a plan?
当然有计划
Of course, we have a plan.
这个计划可能需要再计划一下
Uh, I think the plan might need more planning.
认识你很高兴
It was nice knowing you!
我得调整一下绳子  有点紧了
Hey, I need to readjust the harness. It's a little too tight.
-这绳子应该够长了  -"应该"
- This should be enough rope. - Should be?
我们不知道具体有多深
We don't know exactly how far down it is.
那是我们所有的绳子了
It's also all the rope we have.
好了  要做的话就得快点
Okay, if we're gonna do this, we gotta do it fast.
关吉  告诉他我们的计划
Gwangi, tell him the plan.
-天啊  -听好
- Oh, boy. Oh! - Listen up.
拉一下表示继续往下  两下表示停
Pull once to go lower, twice to stay put,
三下表示上来
three times to come up.
四下表示你到底了
Four pulls means you've reached the bottom
我们可以安全下去
and it's safe for us to come down.
慢着  第二个是什么来着
Wait. What was the second one?
其实根本不重要
Look, it doesn't really matter.
安全词是"神秘生物"
Your safe word is "Mystical creature."
其实那算个短语了
That's more of a phrase, really.
如果你大喊出来  我们会
If you shout it, we'll
停止任务  把你拉上来
abort the mission and pull you right on up.
"救命"如何  我大喊"救命"  简短有力
How aboutjust "Help"? I'll scream, "Help!" Nice and short.
你会做的很棒的
You're gonna do great.
是吗  你真的这么认为
Yeah? You really think so?
开始吧
Let's do this!
米果
Migo!
如果你死了  你的东西能都归我吗
If you die, can I have all your worldly possessions?
-福林  -好吧  抱歉  等你死了
- Fleem! - Right. Sorry, when you die.
看到什么了
What do you see?
目前为止只有云  还是云
Uh, so far just seeing cloud, and more cloud.
慢着慢着  那是什么
Wait. Wait. What is that?
-不  -抱歉  是我的手
- Oh, no! - Sorry, that was just my hand.
好吧
Okay.
还是云  更多的云
Still clouds. More clouds.
-糟了  -云还真多啊
- Uh... - Man, there's a lot of clouds.
-咪琪  是你吗  -索普来了
- Meechee, you out here? - Thorp!
怎么了
H-Oh? Why "h-oh"?
糟糕  神秘生物
Uh-oh. Mystical creature!
你们几个在这里干什么
Hey, what are you freaks doing out here?
神秘生物
Mystical creature!
那是什么
Uh, what was that?
是风
Uh, it's the Wind!
-什么  -风在这里发出奇怪的声音
- Huh? - Yeah, it makes strange noises out here.
神秘生物
Mystical creature!
别闹了  你们举止很奇怪
Stop it. You're all acting weird.
我不喜欢奇怪  让人感觉很奇怪
I don't like weird. Weird is weird, okay?
我好像听到了米果高亢的
I thought I heard Migo's high-pitched,
烦人的声音  他在哪里
kind of annoying voice. Where is he?
-挂在...  -说实话
- Hanging over the-- - Honestly,
我们不知道他在哪里
we have no idea of the status of his whereabouts.
拉几下表示上去
How many times was up?
拉几下
How many times?
有什么事不太对  我想想
Something's not right here. Let me think about this.
有什么事对不上
Ugh, something's not adding up.
我算不太清
Yeah, I can't do math.
你们跟我来
You're coming with me.
不
Oh, no!
绳子显然不够长
Definitely not enough rope!
各位
Guys?
天哪
Oh, boy.
这里根本不是虚无
This is so not nothingness!
这里有好多好多东西
This is definitely something-ness.
天哪  瞧瞧你
Oh, my gosh! Look at you!
小家伙
Hi, little guy!
不
Oh! No!
这太残酷了
That is just harsh!
我来给你个教训  接招
I'll teach you a little lesson. Take that!
好耶
Yes!
快跑  小家伙  跑  去吧
Run, little one! Run! Run! Be free!
那个闪闪发光的会飞的东西
Ooh! The shiny flying thing!
小脚怪
A smallfoot.
不不不
No. No, no, no!
不  石头  石头
No! Rock! Rock!
不  不不不
No. No, no, no.
好了  等等  等等
Okay, okay, back up, back up.
你想采访一个声称看到雪怪的人
You wanna interview a man who says he saw a yeti?
你还真信他的话
And you actually believe him?
当然不信了  但是这能做一期好节目
Of course not. But it makes for good TV.
那个人起了高原反应
That man has altitude sickness.
他需要救助
He needs help!
-等他帮完我们再说  -什么
- After he helps us. - What?
布兰达  你知道这个村庄是为什么而闻名吗
Brenda, do you know what this village is famous for?
雪怪
Yetis.
这个星球上没有哪里
More reported yeti sightings
比这里出过更多的雪怪目击事件
here than anywhere else on the planet.
所以呢
So?
试想看
Picture this.
我们来这里寻找喜马拉雅跳蛛
We're here looking for the Himalayan jumping spider,
结果拍到了雪怪
but we capture on film a yeti.
我们发布视频  肯定会被大量转发  爆炸新闻
We post the video. It goes viral. Then boom!
我的收视率一路飙升
My ratings skyrocket!
雪怪根本不存在
Yetis don't exist.
是吗
Or do they?
我今天到镇上搞了套变装  很像
Picked up a suit in town this afternoon, and it's a cracker.
里面还带高跷
Has stilts and everything.
你要穿上这个欺骗你的粉丝
You're gonna put that thing on and deceive your fans?
当然不是  我会出镜采访
Of course not! I'll be on camera.
变装的是你
You'll be in the suit.
你怎么了
What has happened to you?
那个热爱动物  激励我去热爱动物的
Where is the Percy Patterson who loved animals,
正直的珀西・帕特森去哪里了
who inspired me to love them, who had integrity?
我很正直啊
I have integrity.
好吧  对  我要做一件不正直的事
Okay, yes, I've gotta do one thing without integrity,
然后我就一直保持正直了
and then I'll just be all integrity all the time.
我满心都是正直
I will ooze integrity.
全身浸泡在正直里
I shall bathe in it.
我会有一款叫"正直"的运动饮料
I will have a sports drink called "Integrity"
我会授权  不是免费的
that I will endorse, not for free,
但是我会把钱拿去做慈善
but I will take that money and give it to charity.
我就是有这么正直
That's how much integrity I will have!
布兰达  拜托
Brenda... Please.
没人看我的节目
Nobody's watching my show.
你想拯救一个濒临灭绝的物种吗
You wanna save a species on the verge of extinction?
拯救我吧
Save me.
布兰达
Brenda!
我很紧张  这首歌献给我女朋友
Yo, I'm really nervous. This one goes out to my girlfriend.
布兰达  等等
Brenda, wait.
听我解释
Let me explain.
丽莎  你愿意嫁给...
Lisa, will you marry...
*节目刚开始我以为能名声大噪*
*I thought I'd made it Celebrated when I got my TV show*
*但黑子一直黑  我的收视低低低*
*But the haters out there hating Got my ratings low, low, low*
*很难跟那些电臀小狗*
*It's hard to compete with videos of twerking hogs*
*冲浪松鼠和骑狗猴子竞争*
*And waterskiing squirrels and monkeys riding on the backs of dogs*
*好多压力*
*So much pressure*
*行行好  我不是你一直听闻的珀西*
*Have mercy, I'm not the Percy That you've always heard about*
动物探险
珀西・帕特森
好莱坞
*那个珀西很成功  那个珀西非常红*
*That Percy, he was successful, that Percy had a lot of clout*
*当初我站在巅峰*
*Back then, back when I was high on that hill*
*现在我跌落谷底  交不起账单*
*But now I'm broke here on the bottom with no way to pay my bills*
*每天想喘口气都越来越难*
*It's getting harder every day to catch a break*
*所以当我看到机会  我必须要抓紧*
*So when I see a chance then it's a chance I really need to take*
*我只是在想办法东山再起*
*I'm just looking for a way of bouncing back*
*房租到期  我陷入困境将要崩溃
*The rent is due, I'm in a fix and I'm about to crack*
*压力之下*
*Under pressure*
布兰达  我会弥补的
Brenda? I'm making this up on the spot.
*他处于压力之下*
*He's under pressure*
说实话  那真的很棒
Which is impressive, let's be honest.
拜托
Come on!
*布兰达  布兰达  我是个绝望的人*
*Brenda, Brenda I'm a desperate man*
*帮我回到顶峰吧*
*So help me get back on the top rockin' again*
*没有压力*
*No pressure*
*布兰达  布兰达  能否听听我的辩护*
*Brenda, Brenda Won't you hear my plea?*
*全世界都压在我的肩膀上*
*The weight of all the world ls really weighing on me*
*好多压力*
*So much pressure*
*现在不该放弃  我处于生死边缘*
*This is no time to quit I'm on the verge of a hit*
*我决定一定要取得成功*
*And I'm determined To make this a success, yeah*
*布兰达  告诉我你能看到我的全部潜力*
*Brenda, tell me you see all the potential in me*
压力下的彼得・帕特森
*我愿意付出一切换取你的答应*
*I'll do whatever it takes to make you say yes*
*跪在你面前恳求你*
*Down on my knees Begging you please*
*你能告诉我你理解吗  帮我一把*
*Won't you tell me you understand? Lend me a hand*
*你要拯救我  拯救我  拯救我*
*Oh, you gotta save me, save me, save me, save me*
歌词完全不对
Those aren't even the words.
你以为我不知道吗  布兰达
You think I don't know that? Brenda?
布兰达
Brenda?
不不不  那个包  那套衣服
Oh, no, no, no. The bag! The suit!
不
No!
你发现了什么
Hey, what you got there?
没事的
Shh, it's okay.
我肯定离得很近了
I must be close!
在这里
There it is!
我应该自我介绍一下  但我为什么这么害怕
I should introduce myself. Oh, but why am I so scared?
无法沟通
Hmm. No language skills.
这我倒是没预料到
Didn't see that one coming.
不好意思
Excuse me. Um...
布兰达  求你回来
Brenda, please come back.
就这一次  然后我们就正直
It's just this one time. Then we'll do the whole integrity thing.
我保证  收到留言后请给我回电
I promise. Please call me when you get this!
谢谢你  布兰达
Thank you, Brenda! Oh!
你甚至穿上了高跷  我很喜欢
You've even put on the stilts. Oh, I love it.
这套看上去一点都不假  看上去非常真实
And the suit does not look fake. It's actually quite convincing.
拍摄计划是这样的  我从那边...
Okay, here's the shot. I'll film over...
他一直在说话  说点什么  笨蛋
He's doing all the talking. Just say something, you idiot.
来吧
Here we go.
我是米果  我...
I'm Migo, and I have...
我的乖乖  吼得真棒
Blimey, good growl.
你还装了声音放大器吗
Did you put an amplifier inside there or something?
这就是我和你合作的原因
This is why I work with you,
布兰达  你只要接下任务肯定全力以赴
Brenda. When you're in, you're all in.
好了  发型看上去不错
Okay, hair looks good.
一点背光很棒
Nice bit of back light.
来吧  雪怪发现拍摄  第一次
Here we go. Yeti discovery shot, take one.
我是珀西・帕特森  正在喜马拉雅山高海拔区域
Percy Patterson here high in the Himalayas.
我正在寻找珍稀的...
I was looking for the rare...
还没到你  谢谢  切掉这段  三  二...
Not yet. Thank you. Cut that bit out. In three, two...
我正在寻找稀有的喜马拉雅跳蛛
I was looking for the rare Himalayan jumping spider,
但我刚听到从那个方向传来了一声吼叫
but I just heard a low growling coming from this direction.
那是一只雪怪吗
Is that a yeti?
吼叫
Do the growl.
不好意思
Do you mind?
布兰达  你能关掉吗
Ugh. Brenda, will you turn that off?
我正在拍摄布兰达...等等
I'm trying to shoot Brenda in this... Wait a minute.
布兰达
Brenda?
这是个雪怪  这是个雪怪  这是个雪怪
It's a yeti! It's a yeti! It's a yeti!
我叫不出来了
I can't seem to shout.
要是你知道  在我的世界里
You know, you'll laugh because, in my world,
大家都觉得你们是可怕的怪兽会笑死...
everyone thinks you're this terrifying monster that's all...
但我觉得你一点都不可怕  你好可爱
But you don't look terrifying to me. You're adorable.
小脚怪之歌  我知道  我知道
Ooh, the smallfoot song. I know this one. I know it. I know it.
那样不对吗
Was that not right?
我只需要把你带回家
I just need to take you home
向大家证明
and prove to everyone that
你的存在  然后就不会被驱逐了  好吗
you exist so I can get un-banished. Okay?
你想带点什么吗  好吧
You wanna bring anything? Okay.
那个也想带上吗  好的  过来
You wanna bring that, too? Okay, come here.
那看上去不错
Ooh, that looks cool!
不
No!
等等  你要去哪里
Whoa, whoa. Wait! Where you going?
看看你这兴奋的样子
Look how excited you are.
住手
Stop it!
这太讽刺了
That's ironic.
小脚怪  喂
Smallfoot? Hello?
应该会掉出一颗来吗
That supposed to fall out like that?
我们得放回去  原来是在这里的吧
Hmm, we need to put that back in there. It goes there, right?
天啊
Oh, boy.
好吧  带上这个
All right, take a little bit of that...
希望你不要介意  不过我要带你回家了
I hope you don't mind, but I'm taking you home.
我会说"你们好啊"
I'm gonna be all like, "Yo, what's up?"
他们会说"那是...什么"
And they're gonna be like, "Yo, is that a... What?"
然后我就会一脸"没错"
And I'm gonna be like, "Yeah!"
他们就会一脸震惊
Their faces are gonna be like, "Ahhh!"
然后我就会叫起来
Then my face is like, "Uh-huh!"
小脚怪是存在的  吃瘪吧
Smallfoot exists, sucka. Whoa-hem.!
那是暴风雪吗
Is that a blizzard?
你没事吧
You okay?
这风暴真是太突然了  对吧
Wow, that storm came out of nowhere, didn't it?
别担心  我们在这里等着  这里温暖舒适
Don't worry. We'll wait it out in here. It's nice and warm.
不
Aah! No!
拜托不要死  拜托不要死  拜托不要死
Please don't die. Please don't die. Please don't die.
别担心  小脚怪  我会救你的
Don't worry, smallfoot. I'm gonna save you.
我会救你的  坚持住  坚持住
I'm gonna save you. Just hang on! Hang on! Hang on!
火
Fire.
多么温暖
So warm.
多么舒适
So nice.
等等  怎么...
Wait a minute. What's...
不  不  你不能
No, no, you can't...
怎么样  每一面都烘烤得舒舒服服
How's that? Nice and toasty all the way around.
怎么了
Oh, hey. What's wrong?
你饿了吗  我给你找了吃的
You hungry? I found your food.
不要
Please...
你还冷吗
You still cold?
我知道为什么  你根本没有毛
I can see why. You have, like, no fur.
你的茧快干了
Oh, your cocoon is almost dry.
我给你清出一块地方来
I'll clear off a space where you can
让你能好好躺着等风暴过去
just lie down until the storm passes, okay?
我是珀西・帕特森  这可能是我最后一段视频
Percy Patterson here in what might be my last broadcast ever.
我可能会被吃或者被烤或者被冻死
I might get eaten or roasted or frozen solid
或者这三者的恐怖结合
or some horrible combination of the three.
但是你们要知道
But know this.
知道知道我冒生命危险追寻一些非常了不起的东西
Know that I risked my life in pursuit of something extraordinary.
比我们更大[伟大]的东西
Something bigger than us.
字面意义上的更大
Literally, so much bigger.
太好了  你会动了  我快清理出一片区域
Oh, great! You're moving. I've almost finished clearing off...
我觉得他在说他要拿我当晚餐
I think he's saying he wants to have me for dinner.
好吧  好吧  好吧
Okay, okay, okay, okay.
怎么回事
Oh, what?
拜托  冻僵的蠢手指
Come on, you stupid frozen fingers!
好了
There we go.
布兰达  行行好
Brenda, give me my glory.
上传这段视频  然后派人来帮忙
Upload this video, then send help.
拜托能发  拜托能发  拜托能发
Please work! Please work! Please work!
太好了
Yes!
连接中
已连接
上传时间
28小时
不
No!
这里还有别的东西
Something else is in here.
根据回声判断
Judging by the echo,
我估计距离大概为200米远
I'd estimate distance is approximately 200 meters.
估计错误
Estimation wrong.
我丈夫正在里面睡的正香
My husband is back there sound asleep!
-对不起  对不起  -还有孩子们
- I'm sorry. I'm sorry. - Not to mention the children!
我花了好几个星期才把它们哄睡着
Took me weeks to get them to sleep!
我都没有孩子  但我能想象
I don't even have kids, but I can imagine
这绝对是一件非常困难的事
that is just a really hard thing to do.
我只有六个月的自由妈妈时间
All I get is six months of a little mommy time,
都被你毁了
and you are ruining it!
你就这么走进了我的洞穴  你都没擦干净你的脚
You just walk into my cave. You don't even wipe your feet!
-再一次非常抱歉  -最好真的抱歉
- Again, very, very sorry! - You better be sorry.
我不知道你是什么  或者你从哪里来
I don't know what you are or where you came from,
但你最好学学基本礼仪
but you better learn some manners!
你看到了吗
Did you see that?
她说"你会吵醒我的丈夫"
She was all like, "You're gonna wake my husband."
我说"你得赶紧离开这里"
And I was like, "You gotta get out of here."
然后你完全听懂了  我们在交流
And then you totally understood me. We were communicating.
真是太棒了
This is amazing!
别傻了  珀西
Don't be stupid, Percy.
不要去帮助那个凶猛的大雪怪
Do not go back to help the big, ferocious yeti.
不要这么做
Do not do it!
不过他的确刚刚从一头熊手里救下你
Although he did just save you from a bear.
现在真不是萌生良心的好时机
This is the wrong time to grow a conscience!
没事的  大家伙
It's okay, big fellow.
来把这东西拿下来
Let's get this thing off.
这样疼吗
Does this hurt?
抱歉  这样吗  这样呢
Sorry. This? How about this?
这样呢  这样呢  抱歉
This? This? Sorry.
-住手  -好了
- Stop it! - Got it.
好了  没事了  我没事了
Okay. It's okay. I'm okay.
风暴停了
Oh, the storm's lifted!
不如你和我一起
What do you say me and you
爬到山上  证明你们的存在
get up that mountain and prove you exist?
对  要打手势...
Oh, right. Hand signals. Um...
令人难以置信
This is unbelievable,
但我觉得雪怪是想要和我交流
but I think the yeti is actually trying to communicate with me.
我认为他想要我和他一起走
And I think he wants me to go with him.
这也许是我做过的最勇敢的事
This is either the bravest thing I've ever done
也许是最愚蠢的
or the stupidest.
希望是前者吧
Here's hoping it's the former.
我差点忘了
Oh, I almost forgot.
来  这样应该能让你暖和点
Here. These should keep you warm.
不不不
No, no, no.
其实感觉还真棒
Oh! That's actually quite nice.
我们快到了
We're almost there.
起来了  米果  该敲锣了
Up and at them, Migo. Time to ring the gong!
今天怎么这么累
Why is this so hard this morning?
发射
Launch!
米果
Migo?
米果  该敲...
Migo, time to ring the...
对  被驱逐了
Oh, yeah. Banished.
怎么...
Huh? What the...
两声锣响
Two gongs?
发生了什么
What just happened?
不要问  随他去吧
Don't ask. Just push it down.
随他去吧
Push it down.
我的头盔
My helmet?
放我下去  快点  趁我还没改变主意
Drop me! Quickly, before I change my mind.
你不能这么做  咪琪
You can't do this, Meech!
你是我们的社长
You're our leader!
所以我正应该这么做
Exactly why I should do it!
放我下去
Drop me!
好吧
Okay.
好可怕  真不敢相信米果下去了
This is terrifying. I cannot believe Migo did this.
所以也许  你并不应该去
Which is why maybe, you know, you shouldn't!
我只是想说  我接替你的位置也行
I just wanna say, I'm fine with it being you.
应该我去
I should go.
我很强壮  我一直在自我训练睁着眼睛睡觉
I'm strongest, and I've trained myself to sleep with my eyes open.
我现在就睡着了  你们都是我的梦
I'm asleep right now. You're all part of my dream.
他下去是因为我说服他下去的
He's down there because I convinced him to go!
他可能迷路了或者受伤了
And he might be lost or hurt.
-或者死了  -福林
- Or dead. - Fleem!
怎么了  现在我们就不追求真相了吗
Oh, what? Now we're not about the truth?
我们上次是因为索普来了才把他放了下去
Last time, we dropped him because Thorp showed up,
他可能还会来  所以我们能走了吗
which he might do again, so can we please go?
伙计们  伙计们
Guys! Guys!
我的脑内还在回响着他的声音
Oh, I can still hear his voice in my head.
-伙计们  -我的脑内也是
- Guys! - It's in my head, too.
米果  他在这里
Migo! He's here!
我知道  他永远都会在我们身边
I know. And he always will be.
不不不  他在这里
No, no, no. He's here!
这边
As in over there!
伙计们
Guys!
-米果  -米果
- Migo! - Migo!
神秘生物
Mystical creature!
不
Oh, no! Ahh!
我接住你了
I've got you!
米果
Migo!
我总算放心了
I am so relieved!
-看  我就说他还活着  -我的兄弟
- See? I told you he was alive! - My brother!
米果  米果
Oh, Migo! Oh, Migo.
伙计们  慢点  慢点  慢点
Whoa, whoa! Guys, easy. Easy, easy.
那是什么
What is that?
小脚怪论证社团  来见见你们的神秘生物
Smallfoot Evidentiary Society, meet your mystical creature!
我就知道是真的
I knew it was real.
没有人再会觉得我疯了
No one's gonna think I'm crazy anymore.
他好美
He's so beautiful!
好矮
And so short.
你成功了  米果  你真的成功了
You did it, Migo. You actually did it!
不  我们成功了  SES
No, We did it. The S.E.S.!
四个大脚野人
Wow! Four more Sasquatch.
一大群
It's a whole Sasquad.
恐惧我吧  渺小的生物  我是你们的神
Fear me, little creature. I am your god!
-福林  你在干什么  -树立统治权
- Fleem, what are you doing? - Establishing dominance.
不
No.
我们不统治
We don't dominate.
我们张开双臂欢迎他
We welcome him with open arms.
是我干的吗
Oh, did I just do that?
我很抱歉  你没事吧  你受伤了吗
I am so sorry! Are you okay? Are you hurt?
很抱歉  我爱你  我爱你
I'm so sorry. I love you. I love you.
我们得把这真相带回村庄
We gotta bring this truth to the village,
让他们小吃一惊
blow some tiny minds.
什么意思
What was that?
他们的脑子太小了
Their minds are really tiny.
关吉说得对
Gwangi's right.
我们来叫醒他们
Let's wake them up.
什么  米果回来了
What? Migo's back?
没错  打脸了吧
Yeah, that's right. In your face!
-我的脸  -大家伙儿  听我说
- Oh! My face! - Hey, listen! Everyone!
停下你们手中的活  跟着我
Stop what you're doing and follow us!
这将会是你们今天最棒的见闻
'Cause this is gonna be the best part of your day!
你们都听到米果说的了
You heard Migo. Everybody.
-没错  -米果
- That's right! - Migo?
说你呢  下来
Hey, you up there! Come on down!
来吧  孩子们  你也是  盖瑞  过来
Come on, kids. You, too, Garry. Get over here.
来吧  你们肯定会喜欢的
Let's go! You're gonna love it!
米果  欢迎回来
Hey, Migo, welcome back...
等等  你不是应该被驱逐了吗
Hold on, aren't you supposed to be banished?
-没错  -好吧
- Yep. - Ah, cool.
大家听好了  围过来
Everyone, listen up. Gather 'round.
我保证  你们绝对不会后悔的
I promise, you're gonna wanna see this.
各位雪怪
My fellow yetis,
我们人生中总会出现非常重要的时刻
there are moments in life that are imbued with such importance,
我们需要停下来  好好地
we must pause and look deeper
看看我们自己所处的位置
into the moment of the place in which we are
把握住这美好的时刻
to hold such beauteous gravitas
好好欣赏这...
and take in the beauty--
-我开始觉得无趣了  -直奔主题
- I'm losing interest! - Get to the point!
好吧  来吧
Yep, okay. Here we go.
各位雪怪  请看  小脚怪
Fellow yetis, behold, the smallfoot!
我真不敢相信我的双眼
I can't believe my eyes.
他们不是住在洞窟里的原始野兽
These aren't primitive beasts living in caves.
这是一个复杂的文明
This is a complex civilization.
你知道这对世界来说意味着什么吗
Do you know what this means for the world?
珀西・帕特森独家巨制
A Percy Patterson network special.
不客气  世界
You're welcome, world!
那么...
So...
这次又在热闹些什么呢
...what's all the excitement about this time?
米果找到了小脚怪
Migo found a smallfoot!
是一种可能
That's one guess.
但是  爸爸  你看看这双小脚
But, Dad, look at the small foot!
牦牛的蹄子不是也很小吗
Don't yaks have small feet?
让我把它带到宫殿里
Let me take it into the palace,
确认律石
consult the stones,
然后再决定这是什么
and determine what it is.
万一这真的是小脚怪呢  那说明律石错了吗
What if it is a smallfoot? Does that mean a stone is wrong?
-全都错了  -没错
- They're all wrong. - Yeah.
告诉我们真相
Tell us the truth!
盖瑞  深呼吸
Garry, just breathe.
大家不要惊慌
Everyone, please.
律石上说有问题该怎么做的
What do the stones tell us about questions?
我有好多问题
I have so many questions!
-它从哪里来  -它为什么是粉色的
- Where is it from? - Why is it pink?
-你怎么来到这里的  -它吃什么
- How did you get it here? - What does it eat?
它的脑袋这么小  怎么思考呢
How does it think with such a tiny little brain?
说实话  我和你们一样满肚子疑问
Honestly, I have just as many questions as you do.
-它的角在哪里  -那是它的耳朵吗
- Where is its horn? - Is that its ear?
它想来一口水果吗
Does it want a bite of fruit?
如果律石上说不可能  它怎么会在这里
How is it here if a stone says it can't be?
*世界比我们知道的大*
*It's all much bigger than we know*
-怎么会  -为什么
- How? - Why?
什么意思
What do you mean?
*它只是刚开始在我们面前展开*
*It's only just beginning to unfold*
-我好迷惑  -还有更多需要知道的吗
- I'm so confused. - There's more to know?
*让它都展开吧*
*So let it all unfold*
*我从来不知道还有更多需要知道的*
*I never knew there was more to know*
*这难道不棒吗*
*Isn't it all so amazing?*
*有个神秘的世界等待你去探寻*
*There's a world mysterious there for you to find*
*突然间有更多空间*
*Out of the blue, there was room to grow*
*这难道不疯狂吗*
*Isn't it all kind of crazy?*
*我们都很好奇  这没有什么不对*
*All we are is curious. There's nothing wrong with that*
*去探寻每一个角落*
*So go 'round every corner*
你管这叫艺术吗
You call that art?
*探索每一天天空*
*Search every part of the sky*
-他在干什么  -他真的会飞吗
- What is he doing? - Is he really gonna fly?
*充满惊奇的生活*
*'Cause a life that's full of wonder*
*才是美妙的生活*
*Is a wonderful life*
-花花  坐下  -到我这来
- Blossom, sit. - I got you.
坐下  坐下
Down. Down!
你看你起了个什么样的头
Do you see what you've started?
是啊  你看看他们
Yes! Do you? Look at them!
我们已经在恐惧中生活了太久  爸爸
We have been living in fear for too long, Dad.
我只是想要保护你的安全  咪琪
All I ever wanted to do was keep you safe, Meechee.
我所做的一切都是为了保护村庄和你
Everything I do, I do to protect the village and you.
我不需要你保护我  我需要你聆听我
I don't need you to protect me. I need you to listen to me.
我们所有人
To all of us,
特别是米果
especially Migo!
爸爸  他去到了云层下面
Dad, he went below the clouds.
他们都在和米果说话
They're talking to Migo
因为他有问题  他会听
because they have questions, and he's listening
而不是叫他们随他去吧
instead of telling them to just push them down.
但是  相信我  你是他们的村长
But, believe me, you are their leader,
他们希望那个人是你
and they wish it was you.
你去找米果谈谈他看到的一切吧
So just talk to Migo about what he saw.
拜托你
Please.
你说得对  我的确需要这么做
You're right. That's exactly what I need to do.
谢谢  我就知道你会想通的
Oh, thank you! I knew you'd come around.
我要去找小脚怪了  再见
I'm gonna go get the smallfoot! Bye!
这是发网  类似于一种头巾
That's a snood. It's like a sort of scarf.
这是一种纤维制品  最好别戴上去
That's a fiber supplement. I'd rather not go into it.
那是袜子
That's a sock.
是一种穿在脚和鞋子之间的布
It's a lining between your shoe and your foot.
你不应该这样...
That's not how you're supposed-- Ugh.
我穿了四天呢
Four days I had them on.
你能翻译无形智慧卷轴吗
Can you translate the Scroll of Invisible Wisdom?
是的  其实我正好需要这个
Yes. Actually, I do need this.
好吧
Okay.
那不是智慧
It is not wisdom
绝对也不是无形的
and definitely not invisible.
米果在哪里
Hey, where's Migo?
爸爸  爸爸
Hey, Dad! Dad!
这是不是最棒的一天
Oh, is this the best day ever or what?
爸爸
Dad?
怎么了  你的头盔呢
What's wrong? What happened to your helmet?
我没有敲锣
I missed the gong.
但是天空中的蜗牛还是来了
But the sky snail, it came up anyway.
所以又有一块石律是错的
Whoa! So another stone is wrong.
-真是太棒了  -棒
- This is amazing. - Amazing?
这有什么棒的
What's so amazing about it?
石律应该就是石律
The stones are supposed to be stones, you know?
坚固  可靠  真实
Sturdy, reliable, true.
现在蜗牛自己起床了
And now the snail is just rising on its own?
如果那真的是蜗牛的话
If it even is a snail.
咪琪认为那可能是一团发光的气体
Meechee thinks it might be a flaming ball of gas.
气体
Gas?
我天天用头撞那玩意唤醒一块气体球
I've been banging my head on that thing to wake up a gas ball?
一般我都是因为气体球才醒的[屁]
That's usually what wakes me up.
爸爸  我知道这些改变很可怕
Look, Dad, I know all of this change is scary.
但是也许这是一件好事
But maybe this is a good thing.
也许还有用你的脑袋敲锣
Maybe there's something even
更好的事可以做
better than banging your head against the gong.
但如果我不敲锣了  我就不是敲锣人了
But if I don't ring the gong, I'm not the gong ringer.
如果我不是敲锣人了
And if I'm not the gong ringer,
那我到底是什么
then what am I?
米果
Hey, Migo!
我爸爸想见你
My dad wants to see you.
守石人  真的吗
The Stonekeeper. Really?
你肯定觉得很棒吧  因为他从来就不想见我
Which must be nice for you 'cause he never wants to see me. Heh.
好吧
Okay.
我为什么大声说出来了  好丢人
Why did I shout that out? That's so embarrassing.
又搞砸了  索普
Ugh. Blew it again, Thorp.
爸爸  我去去就回
Hey, Dad. I'll be back.
爸爸
Dad?
看看它们
Look at them.
过去伟大的守石人
The great Stonekeepers of the past.
每个人得到关于
Each one adding new stones
对村庄最好的智慧时  都会加上新的律石
as they received wisdom about what was best for the village.
-这一串看上去很重  -是的
- Robe looks heavy. - It is.
只有坚实的后背才能承载
It requires a strong backbone.
秘密台阶  好吧
Whoa. Secret stairs. Okay.
你要带我去哪里
Where are you taking me?
那么多问题
So many questions.
我该给你一些答案了
Think it's about time I give you some answers.
这是什么
What is this?
米果
You see, Migo...
*曾经雪怪是住在云层之下*
*There was a time when yetis lived beneath the clouds*
*我们幸福生活茁壮成长*
*We were alive and we were thrivin'*
*直到我们遇到了一群小脚怪*
*Till we came across a crowd of smallfoot*
*没错  我们曾经住在那下面*
*That's right, we used to live down there*
*但是下面的行为让我们无法饶恕*
*But there were actions we could not forgive down there*
*虽然他们用不同的称呼*
*And though they used a different nomenclature*
*什么人或人类  给我们展示他们本性*
*Man or human, they showed us human nature*
*虽然我们好奇接近  但他们是危险种族*
*A dangerous species though we approached with wonder*
*他们用长矛和冒烟的闪电攻击我们*
*They attacked with their spears and their smoking sticks of thunder*
*他们叫我们山顶野人  说我们非常骇人*
*They called us Sasquatch, they called us abominable*
*他们追逐我们至死不休*
*They chased us, pursued us their persistence indomitable*
*我们只能逃走躲藏*
*We had no choice but to run and hide*
*否则我们一族都将面临灭绝*
*Otherwise, we surmised we were facing genocide*
*于是我们为了活命爬上了这座山*
*So we climbed this mountain just to stay alive*
*我们知道小脚怪无法在这里生存*
*You see, we knew that up here smallfoot could not survive*
*于是这里在石律上写下了第一条法规*
*So it was here the first law was written in stone*
*这就是我们要知道的真相*
*It was named and proclaimed as a truth to be known*
*我们的世界在一片无尽的云海之上*
*Our world is an island that floats on a sea of endless clouds*
*以后就这样沿袭下去*
*That's how it would be*
*然后我们写下更多法规  更多规矩*
*And then we wrote more laws, more rules to obey*
*为了我们  只有这样*
*For the sake of us all It was the only way*
*才能保护我们不遭到人类的伤害*
*to protect us from all of the human ravages*
*人类造成的各种伤害*
*Heaped upon us by those human savages*
*现在你知道  现在你知道*
*Now you know Now you know, now you know*
*Now you know, now you know*
*新的规则*
*And new rules apply*
*现在你知道  现在你知道*
*Now you know Now you know, now you know*
*所以最好还是撒谎  撒谎*
*So it's best just to let it lie, let it lie*
*现在你知道  现在你知道*
*Now you know Now you know, now you know*
*Now you know, now you know*
*你无法否认*
*And you can't deny*
*现在你知道  现在你知道*
*Now you know Now you know, now you know*
Now you know, now you know, now you know
*所以最好还是撒谎  撒谎*
*So it's best just to let it lie, let it lie*
但是我的小脚怪不是这样的
But my smallfoot, he's not like that.
他们都是这样的
They're all like that.
告诉我  你找到他时
Tell me, when you found him,
他是张开双臂和你打招呼的吗
did he greet you with open arms?
他们根本不在乎我们
They don't care about us.
他们只在乎他们自己
They don't care about anything but themselves,
所以如果我们还在乎我们的未来
which is why we must do the same,
我们必须要做一样的事
if we care about our future.
我们现在到云层下了
We're below the clouds.
看上去像是云层  但是你再靠近点看
Or so it would seem, but look closer.
这不是云层  是蒸汽
Those aren't clouds! It's steam.
石头很有用
The stones are working.
石头
The stones?
*虽然每件工作  每个任务*
*Every job and every task*
*看上去都毫无意义*
*As pointless as it seems*
*所有的一切都是为了让这个重要的机器
*All of it ensures that this important machine*
*一直运作转啊转*
*Keeps churning and turning and spinning around*
*让下面看不到上面  上面看不到下面*
*So those below don't look up And those above don't look down*
*他们还是会看*
*And they'll look*
*因为就算他们听说过他们的暴行*
*'Cause even if they hear of these atrocities*
*比恐惧更强的只有好奇心*
*The only thing stronger than fear is curiosity*
*现在你知道  现在你知道*
*Now you know Now you know, now you know*
等等  所以这些石律都不是真的  都是谎言
Wait. So none of those stones are true? They're all lies?
*撒谎吧*
*Let it lie*
善意的谎言  为了保护我们的世界
Good lies. To protect our world.
但是他们需要真相
But they need to know the truth.
是吗
Oh, do they?
*你觉得你追求真相是一名勇士*
*You feel emboldened by your noble quest to find the truth*
*而我只会对年轻人的无知而发笑*
*I chalk it up to the naive innocence of youth*
*让我告诉你一个长大后会知道的秘密*
*So let me share a secret that you'll learn as you grow older*
*是真是假全看旁人判断*
*What's true or not true is in the eye of the beholder*
*你想要阻止我们族灭绝吗*
*So do you wanna prevent our own annihilation?*
是的
Yes!
*那我们唯一的目标就是控制信息外泄*
*Then our only goal should be to control the flow of information*
*除非你想看小脚怪攻占村庄*
*Unless you want to see the smallfoot conquer and pillage*
不
No!
*那保护谎言就是保护村庄*
*Then protect the lie and you protect the village*
我们的生命很危险  米果
Lives are at stake, Migo.
你的朋友们  你的父亲  咪琪
Your friends, your father, Meechee.
好吧  我想要知道
Okay. I want to know everything
关于你和你世界的一切
there is to know about you and your world.
她很好奇
She's curious.
你知道俗话说"好奇心杀死雪怪"
And you know what they say. "Curiosity killed the yak."
那你希望我怎么办
So what do you want me to do?
告诉大家你说得关于小脚怪的事是谎言
Tell everyone you were lying about the smallfoot.
但他们都看到了  他们不会相信我的
But they've already seen it. They're not gonna believe me.
他们会相信的事绝对会出乎你的意料
You'd be surprised at what they'll believe.
你觉得知识就是力量吗  米果
You think knowledge is power, Migo?
*现在你知道  现在你知道*
*Now you know Now you know, now you know*
*Now you know Now you know*
问题是
Question is...
*现在你知道  现在你知道*
*Now you know Now you know, now you know*
你准备用那力量来做什么
...what are you gonna do with that power?
好吧  虽然还是不清楚
Okay. It's a little fuzzy,
但我觉得我开始有点搞懂了
but I think I'm starting to get it.
你的工作是让你讲的故事从空中
Your job is to tell stories that fly through the air
奇迹般出现在其他小脚怪家里
in a series of pictures in rapid succession
一系列迅速切过的图片上
that magically appear in other smallfoots' homes.
电视  没错
TV. Right!
那这个东西是什么
And what is this thing here?
那是我家的屋顶
That's the roof of my home.
-家  -家
- Home. - Home?
我们说的是一件事吗
Are we saying the same thing?
那是你最好的朋友吗
Oh, is that, like, your best friend?
那是邪恶的银行家
That is evil banker man.
他想要夺走我的家
He wants to take my home away
因为一个叫"可变利率"的东西
because of something called a "Variable interest rate."
显然我也不知道那是什么意思
Apparently, I don't know what it means either.
这上面的空气真的很稀薄啊
The air is really thin up here, isn't it?
那些是动物
Those are animals.
调皮
Cheeky.
重点就是  这就是我干这一行的原因
Anyway, the point is, this is why I do what I do, see?
我也和你一样  对其他物种非常感兴趣
I was fascinated with other species, like you.
事实上没有和你们一样的  你们太了不起了
Actually, nothing like you. You're quite extraordinary.
但是最近  我开始
But lately, I started to
只在乎有多少人在看
only care about how many people are watching,
我有多火
how popular I am.
真不想听到我自己大声承认...
Hearing myself say this out loud...
雪怪语中的"可悲"是怎么说的
What's the yeti word for "Pathetic"?
我九岁时  第一次看到了狮子
When I was nine, I saw my first lion.
看上去就像这样
It looked like this, see?
看上去一点都不像这样  这看上去像只肥狗
It looked nothing like this. That looks like a fat poodle.
来  我直接给你看吧
Here, I'll just show you.
那是什么东西
Okay. What is that thing?
他们根本不在乎我们  我们的生命很危险  米果
They don't care about us. Lives are at stake, Migo.
他们只在乎他们自己
They don't care about anything but themselves.
善意的谎言
Good lies.
我们必须要做一样的事  保护我们的世界
Which is why we must do the same. Protect our world.
你的朋友们  你的父亲  咪琪
Your friends, your father, Meechee.
不  不要那样
No, don't do that.
你在干什么  你都搞乱了  住手  住手
What are you doing? You're ruining it! Stop! Stop it!
红色上去  上去  现在动蓝色
Red one up! Up, up! Now, over to the blue one.
蓝色  三个一排  太好了
Blue one. Three in a row! Yes!
-咪琪  -忙着呢  米果
- Meechee? - Not now, Migo.
好了  下来  下来  右边  紫色的
Ooh! Okay, down, down. Right side. Purple thingy.
滑下来  滑下来
Slide it, slide it.
好了  轰
Oh! There we go! Boom!
米果  我把一个形状
Migo, I'm putting shapes
放在另一个形状边就能消掉一行行
next to other shapes to make the rows disappear.
这简直是在毫无意义地浪费时间  但我停不下来
It's pointless and a total waste of time, but I can't stop.
游戏结束
那就是我们的最高分
There goes our high score.
小脚怪
Smallfoot?
你没事吧
Hey. Are you okay?
有点困了
Getting a little woozy.
我需要更多氧气  氧气
I'm going to need some more oxygen. Oxygen.
我都记不起我的名字了
I can't remember my own name.
这是什么
What's all this?
我们在学习如何沟通
Oh, uh, we learned how to communicate!
那是他的世界
That's his world...
我觉得非常大
...and I think it's really big,
下面还有更多小脚怪
and there are more smallfeet down there.
非常多
Like, a lot more.
米果  我觉得有点不对劲
Migo, I think something's wrong.
他看上去不大好
He doesn't look so good.
他好冷  他的呼吸很微弱
He's cold and his breathing is off.
我们知道小脚怪
You see, we knew that up here,
无法在这里生存
smallfoot could not survive.
我觉得我们应该把他送回家
I think we need to take him home.
什么  不
What? No!
为什么  万一他很难受呢  万一他需要帮助
No? Why not? What if he's really sick? What if he needs help?
不要再问问题了
Just stop asking questions!
不要再问问题
Stop asking questions?
大家请注意
Attention, everyone!
守石人有事情要宣布
The Stonekeeper has an announcement.
怎么回事  你知道吗
What's going on? Do you know?
你看上去好像你知道些什么
'Cause you look like you know something.
别问了  拜托
Just stop. Please.
今天是多么有意思的一天啊
What an interesting day it's been.
充满了惊喜和问题的一天
A day full of excitement and questions.
那么多问题
So many questions.
我必须承认  今天发生的事甚至让我也萌生疑问
I must admit, the events of the day even had me asking a few.
闻到了掩饰的气息
Uh-oh, I smell cover-up.
于是我邀请米果和我一起
So I asked Migo to join me
我问了他几个关于他的大发现的问题
so I could question him about his amazing discovery.
然后我们一起达成了共识
And together, we've reached the same conclusion.
米果  告诉他们我们都发现了什么
Migo, tell them what we learned.
事实上  那个...
The thing is, see... Uh...
是的  这...
Yeah, it's, uh...
我要告诉你们的是...
What I was gonna tell you is, urn...
这不是小脚怪
It's not a smallfoot.
等等  什么
Wait. What?
我错了  我弄混了
Yeah. I was wrong, I got confused,
守石人发现了
and the Stonekeeper figured it out.
这其实是一种牦牛
It's actually a type of yak.
一种牦牛
A yak?
米果发现了一种
Migo found a rare breed
连我都不知道的新种
that even I didn't know about.
一种红色小型无毛牦牛
A red-coated pygmy hairless yak.
你知道这不是牦牛
You know this is not a yak.
如你们所见  他们的存在在石律上
As you can see, its existence is confirmed
有记载
in stone.
发生了什么
What is happening?
石律世世代代保护着我们
The stones have protected us for generations.
但我们却一直忽视它们
But we've been ignoring them.
今天都没有人去喂大山地猛犸象
No one's been feeding the great mountain mammoths today.
他说得对
He's right.
正因如此  我们在下沉
And because of that, we are sinking.
我不想下沉
I don't wanna sink!
盖瑞  你的害怕是正确的
Garry, you're right to be afraid.
大家听听盖瑞说的话
Everyone, listen to Garry.
我不想下沉到虚无里
I don't wanna sink into the nothing!
这都是谎言  米果  我们看到你去了云层下面
These are lies, Migo. We saw you go below the clouds.
我没有  我跌入云层中
I didn't. I fell into the clouds,
我在一个洞穴中找到了他
and I found him inside of a cave.
什么
What?
别听他的  这全都是在掩饰
Don't listen to him. This is all part of a massive cover-up!
-拜托  等等  -我们都处于一个大机器中
- Please, wait-- - We're all part of a big machine.
哥们  不  拜托  停下
Dude, no. Come on, stop!
其实我觉得下面就应该有一个巨大的机器
In fact, I think it might be a big machine that's down there!
别说了
You need to stop!
-听起来的确像是机器  -我也觉得
- It does sound like a machine! - I thought so, too!
-就是  -别说了
- You heard me! - Just stop!
一个巨大的机器
A big machine.
没错
Right!
我们都听关吉和他的疯狂理论吧
Let's all listen to Gwangi and his whacked-out theories
因为我们都知道关吉
because we all know that Gwangi is
就是个疯子
just straight-up crazy.
-什么  -别说他是疯子
- What? - Don't call him crazy.
拜托  我们真的要听这些人说的话吗
Come on, are we really gonna listen to these guys?
他们都是村里的怪人  我们都知道
They're the village weirdos, right? We all know that.
他们只是想证明这些石律是错的
They're just trying to prove all the stones wrong.
但是如果我们不遵从石律  就会发生很糟糕的事
But if we don't follow the stones, really bad things can happen.
说得好  米果  这就是真相
Well said, Migo. That's the truth.
真相
The truth?
我觉得这里没人在乎那是什么
I don't think anybody around here cares what that is.
伙计们  等等
Guys, wait.
米果  把他给我
Migo, give him to me.
等等  你要做什么
Wait. What are you doing?
不不不  他需要温暖  他无法呼吸
No, no, no! He needs warmth, and he can't breathe!
-咪琪  -你为什么要这么做
- Meechee. - Why are you doing this?
我们应该到里面再来讨论
This is something we should discuss inside.
里面
Inside.
好的  父亲
Yes, Father.
咪琪  我们要谈谈
Meechee, we need to talk.
我觉得你说得够多了
I think you've said enough.
好了  大家伙儿
Okay, everyone.
现在一切都可以恢复原样了
Now everything can go back to the way it was.
大家都回去干活吧  这个村子可没法自给自足
Everyone, back to work. The village won't run itself.
小脚怪  你要对他做什么
The smallfoot, what are you gonna do with him?
我们要把他送回你找到他的洞穴里
We're taking him back to the cave where you found him.
但我不是在洞穴里找到他的
But I didn't find him in a cave.
但你是这么说的  所以他们相信了你
But you said you did, so they believe you.
你做了一件好事  米果
You've done a good thing, Migo.
守石人  等等
Stonekeeper, wait!
不
No!
你已经做了你该做的事  米果
You've done your job, Migo.
回家去吧
Go home.
米果
Migo?
怎么了  你在做什么
What's wrong? What are you doing?
我只是在想15号石律
I was just thinking about Stone 15.
"无知是福"
"Ignorance is bliss"?
没错  这条说得不错
Yeah. That one's true.
无知的确是福
Ignorance is bliss,
至少曾经是
or at least it was.
我当初不知道小雪怪  或者SES
I was pretty happy when I didn't know about the smallfoot
或者咪琪
or the S.E.S.
有多么迷人时  是多么快乐
or how amazing Meechee really is.
而且如果我现在不知道他们恨我
And I'm pretty sure I'd be happier
或者我欺骗并背叛了他们的话
not knowing that they hate me.
我肯定会更开心一点
Or that I lied and betrayed them all.
我真想念无知的时候
I miss being ignorant.
我们还是就回归原来的样子
So let's just, you know, go back to the way things were,
只有一件事变了
with one change.
从现在起我要当敲锣人
I'll be the gong ringer from now on.
也许用我的头去敲那玩意
Maybe banging my head into that thing
能让我忘记这些感觉
will make all of these feelings go away.
没错  你可能会变得麻木  什么都感觉不到
Oh, yeah. You'll pretty much go numb. You won't feel a thing.
很好  因为我感觉我是个混蛋
Good. Because I feel like such a jerk.
好吧
Okay.
你还记得我给你的建议吧
Now, you remember the advice I gave you, right?
首先  检查风向  一点风就能把你吹得偏离正轨
First, check the wind. Pretty easy to get blown off course.
风向  没问题
Wind, check.
然后你得瞄准你的目标
And you gotta true your aim.
如果不瞄准  那肯定不会成功
You'll never succeed if your aim isn't true.
目标  没问题
Aim, check.
别忘了
And don't forget.
即使你知道会很疼
Even though you know it's gonna hurt,
你也得用脑袋径直撞上去
you gotta hit it head-on.
他在里面
He's in there.
她也在里面
She's in there.
但是
But...
你已经叫醒了村民们  儿子
You already woke the village, son.
别让他们再睡回去了
Now, go make sure they stay awake.
我爱你  爸爸
I love you, Dad.
我也爱你  儿子
I love you, too, son.
来  说出那个词吧
Now, say the word.
发射
Launch!
咪琪  我很...
Meechee, I am so...
不
Oh, no.
咪琪
Meechee?
你来这里干什么
What are you doing here?
咪琪
Meechee.
小脚怪在哪里
Where's the smallfoot?
坚持住  小家伙  你马上到家了
Hold on, little guy, okay? You're almost home.
咪琪带走了小脚怪
Yeah, uh, so Meechee took the smallfoot.
她说我有愤怒管理问题
And, uh, convinced me I have a lot of anger issues
因为什么恋父情结
because of something called a father complex.
我不知道  就是因为小时候没有被抱够
I don't know. Something about not getting enough hugs as a kid.
我现在在进行非常认真的治疗  爸爸
Really doing some serious processing right now, Dad.
我都做了什么
What have I done?
开门
Open the door!
伙计们
Guys!
伙计们  你们得帮帮我
Guys! You have to help me!
咪琪带着小脚怪去云层下了
Meechee's taken the smallfoot below the clouds!
听着  对不起  我说的那些话都不是故意的
Look, I'm sorry. I didn't mean what I said.
等我们找到咪琪  我都能解释
I can explain everything, after we find Meechee.
她有危险  你们要相信我
She's in danger. You have to believe me!
我们为什么要相信你  你撒谎  朋友不会撒谎
Why should we believe you? You lied. Friends don't do that.
或者背后捅刀
Or stab you in the back
在所有村民面前说你是疯子
and call you crazy in front of the whole village.
你就像我一样  我本来期待你能更好的
You acted like me. I expect more from you.
你们说的对  我撒谎了
You're right. I lied.
你们一直都在追寻真相
You know, you've always searched for the truth.
不管别人怎么说
No matter what anybody said.
他们笑话你  他们骂你们[叫你们名字]
They laughed at you. They called you names.
等等  什么名字
Wait. What names?
但你从来不会因为恐惧而停下步伐
But you never let fear get in the way.
我也应该那样做的
That's what I should have done.
所以我现在就要这么做
And it's what I'm gonna do now.
米果
ALL: Migo!
等等  什么名字
Wait! What names?
咪琪  你在哪里
Oh, Meechee, where are you?
-蔻卡  -你好
- Kolka! - Hi!
等等  如果你下来了  那说明...
Hi! Wait. If you're here, that means...
天  真是掉了好久
Man! That is a long way down!
伙计们
Guys!
你们来了
You came!
我们当然来了  为了咪琪
Of course, we came. For Meechee.
当然了  我知道
Yeah. Yeah, I know.
以及一点点为你  不过主要是咪琪
And a little bit for you. But mostly Meechee.
谢谢你们  甚至连你  福林
Thank you. Even you, Fleem.
等等  福林在哪里
Wait. Where's Fleem?
好吧  分析利弊
Okay, pros and cons.
利  米果需要你
Pro, Migo needs you.
弊  如果你死了  对他来说就没用了
Con, you're useless to him if you're dead.
弊一比利零  好的  利
Cons, one. Pros, zero. Okay. Pro.
没错  福林真蠢
Yeah, Fleem sucks.
我们等不了了
We can't wait.
我们得赶紧赶在还没人发现咪琪之前找到她
We have to find Meechee right now before someone else does.
真大
It's so big.
我们怎么知道她落到了这里
How do we even know she landed here?
好了  小家伙
Okay, little guy.
你可以好好呼吸了
You can breathe easy now.
你到家了  看
You're home. See?
家
Home.
那是什么
What is that?
等等  我在哪里
Wait. Where am I?
什么
What?
不不不不不
Oh, no. No, no, no.
-布兰达  -珀西
- Brenda? - Percy?
珀西  你还活着
Percy! You're alive!
你还活着
You're alive!
天啊  你还活着  对吗
Oh, my gosh, you are alive, aren't you?
还没死  还能走
Not dead. Raring to go.
知道我冒生命危险
...know that I risked my life
追寻一些非常了不起的东西
in pursuit of something extraordinary.
比我们更大的东西
Something bigger than us.
我的视频
My video.
我照你说的上传了  然后火了
I uploaded it like you told me to, and it went totally viral!
这是真的  对吧  我都做了文化衫
It was real, right? I mean, I have the suit.
你找到了雪怪
You found a yeti.
我的手机都被打爆了
My phone has been ringing like crazy.
所有人都想找你  你都没看信息吗
Everyone wants you. Haven't you checked your messages?
追寻一些非常了不起的东西
...my life in pursuit of something extraordinary.
珀西  我最喜欢的客户  我是你的经纪人
Percy, my favorite client! It's your agent.
我希望你回来  给我回电
I want you back. Call me.
我是国家地理学会的
This is Mark Birden from
马克・伯登  请给我回电
the National Geographic Society. Call me!
珀西  我是你爸爸  不再以你为耻了
Percy, it's your dad! I'm no longer ashamed of you!
这里还是《纽约时报》来电
Hi, this is the New York Times calling again...
我朋友的朋友给我你的号码  我看了你的视频
I got your number from a friend of a friend. I saw your video.
珀西  我是网络台的盖尔
Percy, it's Gayle at the network.
我看到了你的视频
I saw your video!
如果你能活捉那只雪怪  能保住你和你的节目
If you can get that yeti alive, you and your show are saved!
这是你想要得到的一切
This is everything you wanted.
等等  雪怪到这里来了
Wait. The yeti is here?
真不敢相信眼前的一切
I can't believe what I'm looking at.
这真是太美了
This is incredible!
那是什么
What is that?
真美
So pretty.
天啊  一个小脚怪宝宝
Oh, my gosh, a baby smallfoot!
你好可爱
You are so cute!
你可真柔软
Wow, you are so limber!
等等  你不是真的  对吗
Wait. You're not real, are you?
超级尖
Super pointy.
真美
Oh, it's so pretty.
又一个小脚怪
Another smallfoot!
你们到有多少个
How many of you are there?
好多
Oh. A lot.
你们好
Hi.
它们好快
Wow! Those are fast.
伙计们  我到处找过了  咪琪不在
Guys, I've looked everywhere. Meechee's not here.
我觉得我找到她了
Yeah, I think I found her.
真是太美了
Oh, this is amazing!
不不不
Oh, no, no, no.
实在是太亮了
Okay, that's really bright.
怎么回事
What is going on?
你们为什么要这么做
Why are you doing this?
咪琪  我们来了  没事了
Meechee! We're here. It's okay.
谢谢
Thank you.
其实有事  我们现在面对最大的危机
Actually, it's not okay. We're in the worst place ever.
但我们现在在一起
But we're together!
-太好了  -耶
- Yes. - Yay!
等等  福林在哪里
Wait. Where's Fleem?
利10比弊65  太折磨人了
Pros, 10. Cons, 65. Oh, this is torture!
-福林太可悲了  -没错
- Fleem's pathetic. - Yeah.
-你受伤了吗  -我没事
- Are you hurt? - I'm okay.
但是他们为什么突然都要来抓我
But why did they just turn on me like that?
因为他们是可怕的生物
Because they're terrible creatures.
你  你为什么在这里
You! Why are you here?
-你很生气  -不然呢
- You're angry. - You think?
咪琪  我非常  非常抱歉
Meechee, I'm so, so sorry.
但是相信我  我那么说是为了保护你
But believe me, I said what I said to protect you.
保护我  撒谎吗
Protect me? By lying?
她说得有道理  米果
She's got a point there, Migo.
你不是一直也在骗你爸爸吗  SES的秘密社长
Haven't you been lying to your dad, secret leader of the S.E.S.?
他说得有道理  咪琪
He's got a point there, Meech.
这完全不一样
This is completely different.
再说了  你到底觉得你在保护我不受什么伤害
Besides, what did you think you were protecting me from anyway?
不受那个
From that.
这就是你爸爸给我看的  所以我才撒谎
This is what your dad showed me. This is why I lied.
他们是怪物
They're monsters.
不  他们觉得我们是怪物
No, they think we're monsters.
伙计们  他们越来越近了
Guys, guys! Psst! They're getting closer.
他们会找到我们的  我们怎么办
They're gonna find us. What are we gonna do?
我们得赶紧离开
We gotta go. Now.
他们真的全是坏人吗
Are they really all bad?
我不知道
I don't know.
但是我们不能傻傻地在这里等
But we can't wait around here to find out.
他们在那里
Where are they?
我发誓他们到这边来了
I swear they came this way.
找到他们了
Whoa! Found them!
不  你去哪里
Oh, no! Where are you going?
我必须赶在他们之前找到他们
They're not gonna get them before I do!
珀西
Percy!
我们走  快点
Let's go. Come on.
下来简单上去难
Getting down here was easier.
不  米果  我们被困住了
Oh, no! Migo, we're trapped!
不要被光照到
Stay out of the light!
整条绳子
The whole robe.
我就说这些石律是保护我们的
I told you the stones were here to protect us.
爸爸
Daddy!
咪琪
Meechee!
你来找我了
You came for me.
我当然要来了  我聆听了
Of course, I came. I listened.
谢谢你
Thank you.
那是什么
What are those things?
米果  走吧  我们能逃走的
Migo, come on! We can make it.
-快走  -你在干什么
- Go! - What are you doing?
不能让他们跟到我们的家园
We can't let them follow us home.
-米果  -快走
- Migo! - Just go!
不
No!
我来了  来抓我吧
Here I am! Come and get me!
关吉  快走
Gwangi, come on! Gotta hurry.
朋友  对吗
Friends, right?
我希望你理解我为什么要这么做
I hope you understand why I have to do this.
不
No!
不  他们抓住他了
Oh, no! They got him!
-咪琪  -米果
- Meechee! - Migo!
那里
There!
不
No!
该死  你们抓到我了
Oh, darn! You got me.
你觉得这是什么好笑的恶作剧吗
Do you think this is some kind of joke?
那得看情况了  你们觉得好笑吗
That depends. Did you think it was funny?
只是宣传的噱头
Just a publicity stunt for ratings.
混蛋
Loser.
那不是米果  那米果在哪里
That's not Migo! So where's Migo?
他打了我
He shot me.
-米果  -你的小脚怪打中了你
- Migo! - You smallfoot shot me.
我的脸麻了
I can't feel my face!
等等  那他是坏人了
Wait. So he is bad?
不  他不坏
No, no, he's not bad.
我觉得他打我是为了救我
I think he shot me to save me.
没错  你说得对  他救了你
Yeah. You're right. He did.
他救了我们所有人
He saved all of us.
看来我的名气是黄了
Well, there goes my fame.
没错  但是你得到了更棒的
Yeah. But you have something better.
你的正直
Integrity.
我怎么没找到呢
Huh. Where was that hiding?
谢谢你  布兰达
Thank you, Brenda.
你因为扰乱秩序  损坏公共财物
You're under arrest for disturbing the peace,
违反规定
destruction of public property,
燃放大量烟花  网络诈骗
discharging fireworks within the city limits...
等等
Wait. Hang on.
鬼鬼祟祟  奇装怪服
...internet fraud, loitering...
而被捕了
...looking weird.
我爱那个小家伙  我也爱你们
I love that little guy. I love you guys, too.
你是那么棒  那么聪明
And you are so awesome and smart,
我先你  我向你
and I'm meet you. I mish you.
我香你
I mush you.
我也香你  米果
I mush you, too, Migo.
好了  我们先回家吧
Okay, everyone, let's go home.
好了  我错过了什么
Okay, what'd I miss?
这是我们的过去  这些是我们的祖先
This is our history. And these are our ancestors.
曾经  雪怪都是住在
There was a time when yetis lived
云层之下的
beneath the clouds.
我们搬到了这个小脚怪无法生存的高度
We came up here where the smallfoot couldn't survive.
我本来以为
You see, I thought the
小脚怪是我的敌人  但他却救了我们
smallfoot was my enemy. And then he saved me.
我知道我之前说那不是小脚怪
And I know that I said it wasn't a smallfoot,
但那不是真的
but that wasn't true.
我很抱歉我骗了你们
And I'm sorry that I lied to you.
小脚怪是真的  他们住在云层下
The smallfoot is real, and they live below the clouds.
那些云是我们创造出来的
Clouds we make.
这是我们的祖先决定这么做的原因
And this is why our ancestors decided to do that.
那是真的  你们看
That's the truth. See?
这很复杂  也很可怕
It's complicated, and it can be scary,
但总比活在一个谎言中好
but it's better than living a lie.
好太多了
Like, way better.
那我们不是从伟大的天之牦牛屁股中掉下来的
So we didn't fall out of the butt of the great sky yak?
可能不是
Probably not.
那我们是从谁的屁股上掉下来的
Whose butt did we fall out of?
-我们回头再聊吧  -明白了
- You know what? We'll circle back. - Got it.
现在你们知道了
So now you know.
我们觉得他们是怪物  他们觉得我们才是
We think they're monsters, and they think we are.
如果我们躲起来  这一切都不会改变
And that is not gonna change by us hiding.
我们需要沟通
We have to communicate.
所以现在得由我们来决定想要怎么做了
So it's up to us to decide what we wanna do.
*是时候了  该做些*
*It's time. Time to do*
*伟大的事  新鲜的事*
*Something drastic, Something new*
*此时  此地*
*Right here snd right now*
*我们得想办法*
*We need to find a way somehow*
*该伸出手  拉近距离*
*It's about reaching out closing up the distance*
*不要互相憎恨  庆祝我们的不同*
*Instead of hate, celebrate all the ways we're different*
*我是乐观主义  没错我相信*
*I am optimistic, yes, I do believe*
*我们能让这个世界变得更好*
*We have the power to make this world a better place*
*但是如果想要改变  你我必须齐心*
*But if it's ever gonna change we gotta come together, me and you*
*互相敞开心扉*
*In a mo-oh-oh, oh-oh A moment of truth*
*如果想要改变
*If it's ever gonna change*
*你我必须齐心*
*We gotta come together, me and you*
*互相敞开心扉*
*In a mo-oh-oh, oh-oh A moment of truth*
我没有疯
I'm not crazy!
利  如果你下去  你会遇到很多人
Pro, if you go down there, you'll meet lots of people.
弊  你其实不喜欢很多人
Con, uh, you're not really a people person.
这太折磨人了
Oh, this is torture!
好吧  三  二...
Okay, in three, two...
下一集的...
On the next episode of...
等等  我缺了一颗牙吗
Wait. Am I missing a tooth?